President Donald Trump: My fellow
Americans: Tonight, I want to
speak with you about our
nation's unprecedented response
to the coronavirus outbreak that
started in China and is now
spreading throughout the world.
Today, the World Health
Organization officially
announced that this
is a global pandemic.
We have been in frequent contact
with our allies, and we are
marshalling the full power of
the federal government and the
private sector to protect
the American people.
This is the most aggressive and
comprehensive effort to confront
a foreign virus
in modern history.
I am confident that by counting
and continuing to take these
tough measures, we will
significantly reduce the threat
to our citizens, and we will
ultimately and expeditiously
defeat this virus.
From the beginning of time,
nations and people have faced
unforeseen challenges, including
large-scale and very dangerous
health threats.
This is the way it always
was and always will be.
It only matters how you respond,
and we are responding with great
speed and professionalism.
Our team is the best
anywhere in the world.
At the very start of the
outbreak, we instituted sweeping
travel restrictions on China and
put in place the first federally
mandated quarantine
in over 50 years.
We declared a public health
emergency and issued the highest
level of travel warning on other
countries as the virus spread
its horrible infection.
And taking early intense action,
we have seen dramatically fewer
cases of the virus in the
United States than are now
present in Europe.
The European Union failed to
take the same precautions and
restrict travel from
China and other hotspots.
As a result, a large number
of new clusters in the United
States were seeded by
travelers from Europe.
After consulting with our top
government health professionals,
I have decided to take several
strong but necessary actions to
protect the health and
wellbeing of all Americans.
To keep new cases from entering
our shores, we will be
suspending all travel from
Europe to the United States for
the next 30 days.
The new rules will go into
effect Friday at midnight.
These restrictions will be
adjusted subject to conditions
on the ground.
There will be exemptions for
Americans who have undergone
appropriate screenings, and
these prohibitions will not only
apply to the tremendous amount
of trade and cargo, but various
other things as we get approval.
Anything coming from Europe
to the United States is what
we are discussing.
These restrictions will also not
apply to the United Kingdom.
At the same time, we are
monitoring the situation in
China and in South Korea.
And, as their situation
improves, we will reevaluate the
restrictions and warnings that
are currently in place for a
possible early opening.
Earlier this week, I met with
the leaders of health insurance
industry who have agreed to
waive all copayments for
coronavirus treatments, extend
insurance coverage to these
treatments, and to prevent
surprise medical billing.
We are cutting massive amounts
of red tape to make antiviral
therapies available
in record time.
These treatments will
significantly reduce the impact
and reach of the virus.
Additionally, last week, I
signed into law an $8.3 billion
funding bill to help CDC and
other government agencies fight
the virus and support vaccines,
treatments, and distribution of
medical supplies.
Testing and testing capabilities
are expanding rapidly,
day by day.
We are moving very quickly.
The vast majority of Americans:
The risk is very, very low.
Young and healthy people can
expect to recover fully and
quickly if they
should get the virus.
The highest risk is for elderly
population with underlying
health conditions.
The elderly population
must be very, very careful.
In particular, we are strongly
advising that nursing homes for
the elderly suspend all
medically unnecessary visits.
In general, older Americans
should also avoid nonessential
travel in crowded areas.
My administration is
coordinating directly with
communities with the largest
outbreaks, and we have issued
guidance on school closures,
social distancing, and reducing
large gatherings.
Smart action today will
prevent the spread
of the virus tomorrow.
Every community faces different
risks and it is critical for you
to follow the guidelines of your
local officials who are working
closely with our federal
health experts --
and they are the best.
For all Americans, it is
essential that everyone take
extra precautions and
practice good hygiene.
Each of us has a role to
play in defeating this virus.
Wash your hands, clean
often-used surfaces, cover your
face and mouth if you sneeze or
cough, and most of all, if you
are sick or not feeling
well, stay home.
To ensure that working Americans
impacted by the virus can stay
home without fear of financial
hardship, I will soon be taking
emergency action, which is
unprecedented, to provide
financial relief.
This will be targeted
for workers who are ill,
quarantined, or caring for
others due to coronavirus.
I will be asking Congress to
take legislative action to
extend this relief.
Because of the economic policies
that we have put into place over
the last three years, we have
the greatest economy anywhere
in the world, by far.
Our banks and financial
institutions are fully
capitalized and
incredibly strong.
Our unemployment is
at a historic low.
This vast economic prosperity
gives us flexibility, reserves,
and resources to handle any
threat that comes our way.
This is not a financial crisis,
this is just a temporary moment
of time that we will overcome
together as a nation
and as a world.
However, to provide extra
support for American workers,
families, and businesses,
tonight I am announcing the
following additional actions:
I am instructing the Small
Business Administration to
exercise available authority to
provide capital and
liquidity to firms affected
by the coronavirus.
Effective immediately, the SBA
will begin providing economic
loans in affected
states and territories.
These low-interest loans will
help small businesses overcome
temporary economic disruptions
caused by the virus.
To this end, I am asking
Congress to increase funding for
this program by an
additional $50 billion.
Using emergency authority, I
will be instructing the Treasury
Department to defer tax
payments, without interest or
penalties, for certain
individuals and businesses
negatively impacted.
This action will provide more
than $200 billion of additional
liquidity to the economy.
Finally, I am calling on
Congress to provide Americans
with immediate
payroll tax relief.
Hopefully they will consider
this very strongly.
We are at a critical time in
the fight against the virus.
We made a life-saving move
with early action on China.
Now we must take the
same action with Europe.
We will not delay.
I will never hesitate to take
any necessary steps to protect
the lives, health, and safety
of the American people.
I will always put the
wellbeing of America first.
If we are vigilant -- and we can
reduce the chance of infection,
which we will -- we will
significantly impede the
transmission of the virus.
The virus will not have
a chance against us.
No nation is more prepared
or more resilient
than the United States.
We have the best economy, the
most advanced healthcare, and
the most talented doctors,
scientists, and researchers
anywhere in the world.
We are all in this together.
We must put politics aside, stop
the partisanship, and unify
together as one
nation and one family.
As history has proven time and
time again, Americans always
rise to the challenge
and overcome adversity.
Our future remains brighter
than anyone can imagine.
Acting with compassion and love,
we will heal the sick, care for
those in need, help our fellow
citizens, and emerge from this
challenge stronger and more
unified than ever before.
God bless you, and
God bless America.
Thank you.